<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Blog By Another Geek]]></title><description><![CDATA[A simple, fixed sidebar two columns Gatsby.js blog starter.]]></description><link>https://sanjana-302.github.io/blogsByGeek</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 21:38:07 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[UPASTHITI - The Real Checker]]></title><description><![CDATA[This blog narrates an incident of me along with my friends Maaz Bin Asad and Apoorve Goyal finding an amazing idea during a general…]]></description><link>https://sanjana-302.github.io/blogsByGeek/introducing-upasthiti/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sanjana-302.github.io/blogsByGeek/introducing-upasthiti/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Oct 2020 07:26:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;This blog narrates an incident of me along with my friends &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/maaz-bin-asad-8a56a2196/&quot;&gt;Maaz Bin Asad&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/apoorve-goyal/&quot;&gt;Apoorve Goyal&lt;/a&gt; finding an amazing idea during a general conversation. We decided to implement it further and I am glad we did it. We received an amazing response from our mentors and it was all worth it. Recently Computer Science Department of our college organized hack - AMU Hacks 1.0. We decided to team up and give shape to our idea. We called it &lt;strong&gt;UPASTHITI - THE REAL CHECKER&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPASTHITI&lt;/strong&gt; means being present/available. Due to the pandemic, most of the things in life went virtual. Our classes were happening virtually. We noticed there was no means for a teacher to check the attention of students towards classes. Most of them were attending but with closed eyes and no voice at all. UPASTHITI was all around this problem. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s see how it works and the tech we used!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A light-weight Face Attendance System( Developed using FLASK, TensorFlow, KERAS-VGGFACE API, MTCNN and, CSVs), with bandwidth checking and reporting capability. The host(or a Teacher) can generate a temporary link for the employees(or students), to mark attendance. The site will first make a check for required bandwidth and if it is above the threshold, the user will be prompted to enter his/her name, after which their camera will turn on for 10 seconds and the photo is captured, matched with the name and image at the backend.
If a match is found, the user’s status is marked PRESENT in a CSV file, else if there is some network error(after max tries), the matter is reported in the CSV automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are currently working on improving it with a Liveliness Detector to distinguish between Real and Fake Identities, and also improving the processing, by integrating APIs and SQLite database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The time factor is something that will allow instructors to keep a check on attentiveness and it is easy to use as it will be an automated process. The task for the instructor is to share the link. Other details will be marked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1KGtdFTKgM6JQGzj09_-4mrXowzDZtSBT/view?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Presenting&lt;/a&gt; the idea was the most important thing that we all learned during this project. As it was a short sprint hack, it was necessary from our side to convey the idea properly to mentors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; We had a wonderful collaboration as a team. Due to different commitments, we couldn’t discuss our stuff during normal hours. I remember all of us waking up early at 5 AM to discuss this project and working till 7 AM for about a week. All of us did multiple things for the very first time and it was all done perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; At last, &lt;strong&gt;UPASTHITI&lt;/strong&gt; shined! We are improving it and soon it will come out better! We earned a special spot in TOP 10 teams. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; The thing that mattered to me the most is bringing a product that can be actually helpful !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Let’s see what life throws next !&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[I analysed Google security!]]></title><description><![CDATA[I remember once scrolling through my Instagram feed I found a post saying : Only 1% of Googlers get to visit Data centers of the company. I…]]></description><link>https://sanjana-302.github.io/blogsByGeek/data-security-analysis/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sanjana-302.github.io/blogsByGeek/data-security-analysis/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 19 Sep 2020 07:26:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt; I remember once scrolling through my Instagram feed I found a post saying :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only 1% of Googlers get to visit Data centers of the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I kept wondering for long about why is it so?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, recently I became interested in data security and cryptography. Here I came to know a lot about it. Instantly I had a thought, why not check how tech giants with massive data are doing it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cannot visit the data centers as of now, but the documentation had some cool stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did a small thesis and it’s all written here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you find this interesting and understand the importance of data security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s dive in!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how it goes in any tech giant that has data of millions of humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make it even clearer I have referred to the Google Data Security Norms mentioned in the official documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://privacy.google.com/businesses/security/#!?modal_active=defense-in-depth-overlay&amp;#x26;article_id=physical-security-to-protect-data-integrity&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for your reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Any data center requires these two modes of security : 
- Physical Security
- Security Protection of Hardware and Softwares &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Distribution of Data across centers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are monitored data centers with locations at multiple places. So If there is any kind of disaster this data can be shifted to locations easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hardware protection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a must. For any upper layers to work hardware protection is a must. No clear techniques have been mentioned in documentations. Customized chips, vetting the vendors, etc are some stated points. I think every company that has massive data centers needs most of its protection and expenditure at this step. This small story itself from the tech giant in the early days of it is a lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sanjay looked at Jeff. For months, Google had been experiencing an increasing number of hardware failures. The problem was that, as Google grew, its computing infrastructure also expanded. Computer hardware rarely failed, until you had enough of it—then it failed all the time. Wires wore down, hard drives fell apart, motherboards overheated. Many machines never worked in the first place; some would unaccountably grow slower. Strange environmental factors came into play. When a supernova explodes, the blast wave creates high-energy particles that scatter in every direction; scientists believe there is a minute chance that one of the errant particles, known as a cosmic ray, can hit a computer chip on Earth, flipping a 0 to a 1. The world’s most robust computer systems, at NASA, financial firms, and the like, used special hardware that could tolerate single bit-flips. But Google, which was still operating like a startup, bought cheaper computers that lacked that feature. The company had reached an inflection point. Its computing cluster had grown so big that even unlikely hardware failures were inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an abstract from a report by The New Yorker. This happened in the year 2000 and is a lesson why hardware requires special attention. You can read the complete report &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2018/12/10/the-friendship-that-made-google-huge&quot;&gt;The friendship that made Google huge&lt;/a&gt;. This will give you deeper insights regarding the handling of data and hardware problems.
Therefore, Data security is a major challenge for any company.
All this gives a glimpse of how data security practices are being carried out in these firms and data breaches are a major concern. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This ends my small thesis regarding the security of data at these giants. Another field known as cryptography now comes into play. The story of encryption and decryption is in itself very interesting. I did not want this blog to introduce technical terms. This was just for purpose of understanding massive data handling. Hope to see you soon in another piece of my work regarding cryptography!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read more about this here.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.google/inside-google/infrastructure/how-data-center-security-works/#:~:text=To%20keep%20our%20customers&amp;#x27;%20data,data%20center%20is%20absolutely%20secure.&quot;&gt;Visiting Google Data Centers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Merrier Days of May - My first pull request]]></title><description><![CDATA[Here, In this write up I talk about my first pull request! When I got myself enrolled at college I saw many of my seniors involved in open…]]></description><link>https://sanjana-302.github.io/blogsByGeek/first-pull-request/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sanjana-302.github.io/blogsByGeek/first-pull-request/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 07:26:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h2&gt;Here, In this write up I talk about my first pull request!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I got myself enrolled at college I saw many of my seniors involved in open-source communities. I hardly understood initially what it was but I had a fantasy to try my hand on this. Will not go in-depth defining it but yes I know what it’s significance is and why is it so important. Open source drives the world. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a fear of doing wrong in public or asking bad questions and so I was dealing with some major personality issues that I figured must be resolved as this was hampering my learning process. I like to code. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started admiring the power of my keyboard and all this happened during this quarantine period as I isolated myself from elements that kinda freaked me out, pulled me back from giving my best, and started discovering newer possibilities of how to make my life more interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thursday, 23 April&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am learning web development.I like JavaScript. It never bores me. I am thinking about making some projects(which ended up in a To-Do-App). I am getting inspired by my connections on LinkedIn as results for Google Summer of Code were out. I remember I took a look at the organisation list, found another alien world with no idea of how should I make myself a place in this world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Friday, 1 May&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I saw a video on “How open source changed my life” somewhere. I felt that I should write some real code now and see how actual systems work. At one point you get bored of just solving some tricky questions and not able to get the point where to use them. So I messaged one of my respected Seniors Rahul Jha, like a layman asking him about some tips which he could lend me so that I could grab some open-source vocabulary. He lent me a ton of his advice and mentioned: “It may be tough but stick to it”. I started googling the words that he made in conversation over chats .”Good first issues” is something that I learned by heart in that conversation. Thank you for all your wise words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Saturday, 9 May&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was going through AMU-OSS slack channel. I saw a message on #general from another respected senior Prateek Jain with its first line stating “Another Good-first-Issue”, that was it. I almost pondered on that message for about 15 minutes thinking should I or should I not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My typical behaviour before I think it’s not the correct time and let things go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully this time I was motivated somehow and with all my will to do something I pinged him asking if I can work on this issue? (Proud of myself I did!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was generous enough to lend me another bunch of tips and ethics to be followed. He worked with me guiding me for about the next 10 days. Answered all my layman question, mentioning everyone do ask them once in a lifetime so that I would feel free to ask him my doubts and not hesitate. Thank you for all your guidance and wise talks.Thank you for teaching me how to write an imperative pull request, commit messages and lot more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Saturday, 16 May&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did not sleep at night on 16 May as I was determined to finish work that was due for my second pull request.This happened after I watched “The Social Network” and came to know that Facebook was built in just 43 days! So I worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sunday, 17 May&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got my two pull requests merged though they were extremely mishandled by me. I did chunk of mistakes but I have no problem with it I learned a lot . I overcame my biggest fear of not questioning my dilemmas and lived my fantasy of contributing open-source earlier than I expected and I am loving it.
I hope my journey in my new alien world goes sound and fruitful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I have learned is that there is nothing like getting back on track. It is always a whole new track in life and we should be prepared for whatever life throws at us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quoted these lines from Michelle Obama’s documentary “Becoming” that I watched during My Merrier days of May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;7 July 2020&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I am redoing this blog. I have seen a huge improvement in myself. From not able to understand words like commit, push, pull etc Now I actually understand workflow of various open source projects. I am not doing any significant contributions lately. I realised I first need to brush up my skills, learn about things that intrests me and then move ahead. This is what I am doing. Let’s see what life throws next! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Signing off! This blog was orignally published on Medium. You can check it here.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[About Myself!]]></title><description><![CDATA[Hey Amigas! I am Sanjana Maheshwari. A Computer Engineering Sophomore at Zakir Husain College of Engineering and technology. I aspire to…]]></description><link>https://sanjana-302.github.io/blogsByGeek/hello-world/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sanjana-302.github.io/blogsByGeek/hello-world/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 07:26:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hey Amigas! I am Sanjana Maheshwari. A Computer Engineering Sophomore at Zakir Husain College of Engineering and technology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I aspire to become an excellent Software Engineer. I like to try new stuff and see what comes out of them. For instance - This blog site is my second attempt. I chose some wrong tech stack and super colorful CSS xD. I messed it. It was a great lesson for me. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I write a lot of code and love learning new algorithms. It gives me the confidence to tackle problems quickly and think efficiently.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I recently became quite interested in cryptography and making some super beginner projects in same. I will try to write about them here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My hobbies include knowing about different cultures and people. I am working with a non-profit organization that aims at imparting education to underprivileged children(This is a story for another blog!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That’s a wrap! The list will elongate in the coming years. Bear with me xD.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thank you!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>